[Music]
hi everybody we are putting this film
out to announce the rebel ISM festival
which is happening on the 30th and 31st
of May and David and I are obviously not
in the same place so we're recording
this remotely so the festival was
originally going to be in person in
London and we've now brought it online
we've also made it free so it's turned
into something I think even bigger and
more ambitious than the in-person
festival and this film is really to
introduce some of the speakers and also
to to introduce the the ethos and that
the whole point of the festival and yeah
what makes it maybe a little bit
different to to a regular online event
we've got all the people that we had
previously for the festival including
Daniel SH macton burger
Jamba Vicky Nora Bateson who we've also
added another couple of speakers
including Douglas rushkoff
and Jamie wheel we designed the festival
to be really participatory so it's not
just about the intellectual side it's
also about the the practical side of
learning new skills levelling up
improving our discernment improving our
focus and our awareness so with that in
mind we have 20 odd workshops with lots
and lots of different practices
so there's mindfulness there's breath
work there's discussion groups
there's circling we've designed it so
that it's a kind of
choose-your-own-adventure format
I'm right now in the middle of the
pandemic and the systemic crisis that
we've also talked about what we found is
these skills become hugely important for
us to navigate and if you prefer not to
participate but you'd like to watch
we're going to be streaming sections of
the festival live to this channel to our
YouTube channel so there's three
different tracks so three different
themes were exploring throughout the
festival and they are sense-making
meaning and imagined futures
sense-making is something we've talked
about a lot how do we make sense of the
world in a world where it's very
difficult now to trust information and
there's a lot of it this is an
absolutely essential skill because if we
don't know how to make sense we don't
know where we're going and the person
who's probably spoken most about
sense-making on the channel and most
eloquently is Daniel Shmack Tim Berger
who's going to be at the festival we're
making more and more consequential
choices with worse and worse sense
making to inform those choices which is
kind of running increasingly fast
through the woods increasingly blind
from what I have seen of rebel wisdom
this is probably the strange attractor
of what is bringing everybody to watch
it is people who are trying to make
sense of the world better themselves and
are trying to find sources of content of
other other people that have been trying
to make sense of it well another key
topic we've talked about in the channel
from the beginning is meaning and maybe
more than anyone else John drove a key
has delved into what he calls the
meaning crisis and he has a whole series
called awakening from the meaning crisis
so John is going to be speaking of the
festival as well and just play a quick
clip at the core of our cognition or our
ability to make meaning it's central to
communication problem solving the
problem that's happened for us is that
the worldview within which our wisdom
traditions arose has been significantly
undermined for a host of very
interconnected and complex historical
reasons that have to do with things like
the process of reformation the emergence
of the scientific worldview so for a
whole host of historical reasons we have
a worldview in which we as meaning
makers don't belong and if you
watching the channel over the last
couple of months you might have noticed
we put out some pieces looking at the
current crisis we're in from a systems
level and pointing out that a lot of
system theorists for the first people to
point out that our systems are
incredibly fragile and one of them is
Nora Bateson who has a really
interesting take on what how systems
work and why it's important that we take
that that wider view the curse of
Cassandra is to be able to see the
future but to have no one believe you
and I think e if you're looking at
multiple systems simultaneously and
complexity thinkers have been actually
and systems thinkers have been saying
for decades I mean not just right before
this but for decades that there is an
incredible destructive fragility and not
just one of our systems like it's not
just the education system it's not just
the economy it's not just the healthcare
system it's not just the political
system it's it's not just that the world
way technology is in our lives it's all
of those systems simultaneously and more
importantly their fragility is in the
relationship between them so the third
track is called imagined futures and one
of the high points of the festival
something we're both really looking
forward to is going to be a first-ever
dialogue between Douglas rushkoff the
author of team human and someone who's
been documenting Silicon Valley since
the 1980s and Jamie will the author of
stealing fire and someone who's been on
the channel a lot and this will be the
first time they've been in dialogue
together if the digital realm is as
powerful as acid you know what set and
setting are we bringing to it you know
we originally brought the set of you
know human potential and infinite
connection between others and now the
set and setting of the Internet is
extractive surveillance capitalism so if
the world is now living in a psychedelic
substrate for the last 20 years
with a sentence setting of extraction
abuse manipulation and and surveillance
capitalism you know no wonder we're
having a bad trip you know this this
this is where we're at and I understand
people are having this they're waking up
into a nightmarish bad trip yeah and
another person like rushkoff who's been
tracking these these wider trends and
looking at the history of the
counterculture from really the the 60s
up until now is eric davis we've also
had in the channel because of the spread
of technology a digital technology of
media of smartphones of the internet of
social media that for a variety of
reasons the way that consensus reality
was structured in the past even in the
immediate past is eroding and as it
arose as it becomes harder to let's say
distinguish between the online world and
our physical world because now our
phones are with us everywhere the
sensors are with us everywhere we're
mapping this real space to this space
and going back and forth more and more
and we're looking at our phones all day
long we're like interrupting or physical
reality reality with these information
flows those two worlds begin to kind of
break down and Eric will be in
conversation with Greg Thomas who's been
on the channel before as well and really
trying to place the the moment in time
we're in now in the historical context
of counterculture history you have folks
that are listening deeply which is
another very important practice in jazz
that we should discuss but they're
coming forth with inflammation in
perspectives that's deeply in form so
that's a snapshot of the rebel ISM
festival again it's happening on May
30th and 31st it's free and supported by
donations so if you want to join go to
rebel wisdom go to UK / festival and
we'll also put that down in the show
notes so hope to see you there and thank
you for watching
[Music]
you